Conclusion

Counting Tagged Words by Plot Section

We included counts of our tagged words for each plot section to show that some of the stories had only four sections. The number of words per section is not necessarily indicative of anything, though it generally correlates with the length of the story. "Old Nurse's Story" is the longest, while "John Charrington's Wedding" is the shortest. The length of the story is an important consideration when considering richness, simply because of how it is calculated.

Except for The Old Nurse’s Story, the “Haunting” section of each ghost story contains by far the largest amount of scary words per story. Both John Charrington’s Wedding and The Shadow in the Corner contain eight times the number of scary words in this section than in their introductions! Again, with the exception of The Old Nurse’s Story, the remaining four follow a general trend, building gradual suspense between the “Introduction” and “Protagonist” sections, displaying climactic scary word clusters around “Haunting” and “History,” and then significantly tapering off the at the “Resolve.” This is almost identical to the traditional dramatic structure chart, but with different plot points. These general trends may reflect the structure of the genre, but may also reflect our preconceived ideas about structure, as we were very conscious of those tropes as we did markup.

Scariness Value by Story

In the “Number of Scary Words per Scariness Rating per Story” graph, we see that most stories contain mostly scary words rated 1 or 2 and relatively few intensifiers. Including 0 and intensifier ratings, John Charrington’s Wedding contains the least amount of possible scary words at 93, while Walnut-Tree House contains the most with a whopping 583 possible scary words. The same holds for true scary words—words with scariness ratings of 1-3—with John Charrington’s Wedding coming in at 80 and Walnut-Tree House at 476. The Old Nurse’s Story has 101 scale-3 scary words, making it the Victorian ghost story with the highest number of scariest words, while John Charrington’s Wedding again comes in last place with only 23.

While we have not taken length of story into the data, it's interesting to see that there are consistently more scale-1 and scale-2 words per story. Fear, then, is more about key moments of suspense, rather than maintaining spookiness throughout.

We also see a general antipathy toward intensifiers. Whether this was on the part of the authors or the taggers is an issue we would like to address. Our markup, while complete, lacks some of the objectivity that a second pass reader could offer.

Scariness by Part of Speech

The scariest type of words per story, according to part of speech, are nouns, with a combined total of 99 scale 3 words in all five ghost stories. The least scariest type of words are adverbs and modifiers, with combined totals of 4 and 1 respectively. Adjectives were a close second for scariest word type, with a combined total of 90 scale 3 scary words, though we had originally suspected they would take the cake. The most action oriented ghost story was The Old Nurse’s Story, with 26 scale 3 verbs, while the most passive was John Charrington’s Wedding with only 1.

Richness of Expression of Scariness

Based on our WordNet analysis and the resulting vocabulary richness ratios, the story with the greatest diversity in vocabulary is John Charrington’s Wedding. We found this particularly interesting in light of the fact that John Charrington’s Wedding is the shortest of the ghost stories in our corpus. It is tempting to think that a longer story would include more variation in scary words, but there seems to be no direct correlation between the richness of the expression of scariness and the length of the story. The story with the lowest vocabulary richness ratio is The Shadow in the Corner, which is squarely in the middle in terms of length with respect to the other stories.

Our data indicates that lexical diversity in scary words is most likely a factor of literary choices on the part of the writer. For instance, the two ratios of vocabulary richness within the closest range of one another are those associated with The Old House in Vauxhall Walk and Walnut-Tree House, both written by Charlotte Riddell. Some authors are prone to repeating certain words, perhaps for emphatic effect, whereas other authors incorporate a wider range of chill-inducing vocabulary, engendering suspense by keeping the reader on their toes.

The richest story is John Charrington's Wedding, which we've judged to be one of the least suspenseful reads. The ghost is not revealed until the end: the story is sweetly sad rather than terrifying. It can be read as the most narratively complex, and perhaps the most literary story we include. It also fails to conform to the narrative tropes we assigned to it, completely forgoing any substantive resolution for a more broad, interpretive conclusion. This leads us to believe that richness of synsets may correlate positively with what we call "literary value," a quality which we can't really encode.

Were we to expand our data to include ghost stories of canonical literary value, like those from Dickens, we hypothesize the richness of language ratio would be comparatively high. This hypothesis also leads to historicist questions of class and gender politics, as vocabulary richness may be indicative of education level of the audience or author.

Conclusion

From our current data, we find that female authors writing Victorian ghost stories typically built suspense in two ways: (1) With a standardized plot structure; and (2) by using scary adjectives to describe scary nouns. In the Victorian ghost story plot, action gradually rises until the ghost appears, where it climaxes and then slowly dissolves as the protagonist finds some way to bring peace the situation. Despite the genre-specific tropes of "Haunting," "History," and "Protagonist," this more or less the pattern of most stories in the Western tradition. At a syntactic level, the norm seems to be to focus on the ghost or haunted house itself as the object of fear, increasing tension through describing its features and, to a lesser extent, by what the object actually does. This perhaps made the stories more accessible to middle-class readers, the authors relying more heavily on sensory, visceral details than deeply intellectual content. This does not imply that these stories were "dumbed down," but rather that they were meant to be more physically frightening, creating a sense of urgency and tangibility in the ethereal.

While it’s hard to declare objectively which of our five stories is indeed the scariest, we can make a few modest measurements. Walnut-Tree House has the highest number of scary words, but the words The Old Nurse’s Story uses are scarier. John Charrington’s Wedding is by far the shortest text, but displays the greatest increase in scariness from its “Introduction” to “Haunting” sections relative to its size. Perhaps he’d like to step out of his grave and claim the prize?

Methodology

The “Victorian Ghost Stories” project attempts to answer the following research question: In what ways did female authors use language to build suspense in the Victorian ghost story? Our research topic involved the fields of literature, history, linguistics, and digital research methods. Our approach required textual analysis, XML language tools, and the WordNet lexical database.

For our readings, we selected five short stories from four different authors: Walnut-Tree House and The Old House in Vauxhall Walk by Charlotte Riddell; The Old Nurse’s Story by Elizabeth Gaskell; The Shadow in the Corner by Mary Elizabeth Braddon; and John Charrington’s Wedding by Edith Nesbitt. This range generated enough data to compare contemporary texts with different writing styles without sacrificing our ability to perform in depth textual analysis on each individual story. Our model is applicable to larger samples of ghost stories, however, should future digital humanists desire to expound upon our research.

After deciding upon our research question and selecting stories, we next performed a close read and analysis of each text to determine our methodology for markup. We decided that the focus of our exploration should be to find “scary words” and rate them according to scariness, part of speech, and synset, so that we could determine not only what scary language was used, but also in what ways its scariness and frequency affected the stories. We accomplished this by compiling a list of 286 unique scary words that we then tagged in each text they occurred. The scariness rating was determined by @scale attributes ranging from 0-3, with the additional rating of “i” for intensifiers like “very” or “quite.” Scary words with a scale of 0 had the potential to ignite fear, but were not so used in context, like the words “black” or “cold.” These words could receive higher ratings when appropriate. Scary words with a scale of 3 were the scariest and therefore always scary, like “horror” or “deadly.” This was the most subjective part of the project, though we gave ourselves parameters in that we drew from an agreed upon list.

Part of speech was measured with attribute @pos, with the available options of verb, noun, adjective, adverb, or modifier. We were curious about the way in which scariness was communicated, and this allowed us to see it at a grammatical, literary level. Is scariness more descriptive, such that the most frequent type of scary words are adjectives? Or is it more action based, such that they are verbs? This data influenced our conclusion, adding another level of specificity to our research question.

As one of our team members had a linguistics requirement to fill, we also explored our scary word elements using the WordNet lexical database. WordNet is a hierarchical organization of units of meaning, called synsets, which are represented in texts by words. A detailed explanation of how synsets can be used to explore a text can be found here. Our project in particular focused on task number three, “Exploring the richness of the expression of spookiness.” We concentrated the task on the “haunting” plot section of each ghost story, expecting that this specific section would incorporate the most significant amount of scary vocabulary. After tagging each scary word element in the haunting sections with its appropriate synset in context, we were able to examine the language that different writers and texts employ to represent scariness. We performed this linguistic investigation by dividing the number of distinct synsets by the number of scary words with a non-zero scariness rating. The resulting value for each text provides a ratio, for which a higher value indicates that scariness is expressed in a wider variety of morphological ways, whereas a lower value indicates less variety in vocabulary.

After tagging all of our scary words, we then measured the number of scary words with a rating of "3" by part of speech in each story using XSLT. We represent this data in SVG bar graphs. We also measure the placement of scary words to determine exactly where these authors built suspense. Do more scary words appear in the beginning of the story, or near the end? Are scarier words clustered together? As mentioned in our synset methodology, we divided the text into five plot points—"introduction," "protagonist," "history," "haunting," and "resolve"—and represented our data using XSLT and EXide to create an SVG bubble chart.

These plot points were attributes of the empty element plot, which we used as a milestone in our markup. "Introduction" represents the introduction to the story, where the setting and scenario is established. "Protagonist" signifies the introduction of the main character, which has a unique trope in Victorian ghost stories. "History" signifies the moment when a character begins recounting the history of the ghost to the protagonist. "Haunting" signifies the beginning of the ghost’s actual haunting of the protagonist. "Resolve" occurs when the protagonist begins looking for a way to resolve the situation, usually bringing peace to the troubled ghost by righting some wrong that was done to it. Using these elements as milestones, we were able to determine whart types of scary words each section contained, how scary those words were, and how often they appeared. Visualizations for our findings is shown in detail on our analysis page.

Background

The “Victorian Ghost Stories” project arose out of our team leader, Gabi Keane’s, interest in supernatural Victorian literature garnered from previous research performed at the University of Pittsburgh. Our basic goal was to explore short ghost stories written by female English authors during the Victorian Era and uncover some unique insight or claim about how they used language to build suspense. After concluding that the stories shared structural and thematic elements, we became curious as to what “scary words” were used to build suspense and how, if at all, the class or education level of the audience impacted the type of vocabulary these authors used to communicate.

Academic Context and Narrative

Many of the assumptions we make about these texts are based on Professor Twyning's observations, discussions, and ever-evolving ideas on the Victorian short story. After reading and discussing the stories in her class, she developed a five part formula for the short ghost story. The five parts were: introduction, protagonist, haunting, history, and resolve. The introduction set the stage for the haunting, often with a physical description or lengthy exposition. The protagonist section introduces a hero; almost always a middle class man who believes the ghost is a problem he can solve. The haunting is self-explanatory, but we should note that it often involves an unresolved issue of justice. It could be wrongful inheritance or a lifetime of neglect, but essentially the ghost is seeking some kind of retribution or resolution. History is generally part of the protagonist's desire to solve the mystery. In order to move forward, he must understand what went wrong in the life of the ghost. The resolve can be an actual resolution, or merely a resignation that the ghost will be tormented forever. The narrative structure of Victorian literature we used to form these ideas are based mostly on Colin MacCabe’s “Realism and the Cinema: Notes on Some Brechtian Theses,” Fredric Jameson’s The Political Unconscious: or Narrative as a Socially Symbolic Act, and (of course) the venerable Raymond Williams. When Professor Twyning inevitably writes an article explaining these tropes and theories in all their glory, we will gladly link to it here.

Choosing the Texts

For our readings, we selected five short stories from four different authors: Walnut-Tree House and The Old House in Vauxhall Walk by Charlotte Riddell; The Old Nurse’s Story by Elizabeth Gaskell; The Shadow in the Corner by Mary Elizabeth Braddon; and John Charrington’s Wedding by Edith Nesbitt. We chose multiple authors to measure for consistency across genres as opposed to one particular artist’s breadth of work. We are using this group as representative of the genre. While the tropes present in these stories cannot be applied to all supernatural fiction of the period, we believe they do represent the trends. Note that popular canon writers like Dickens often subvert these tropes (and often to great effect).

Acknowledgements and Citations

Stories by Charlotte Riddell and Elizabeth Gaskell were republished thanks to gothictexts.wordpress.com. John Charrington’s Wedding by Edith Nesbitt was available for free via Project Gutenberg. The Shadow in the Corner was republished with permission from gothichorrorstories.com.

We would like to extend a special thanks to our project mentor, Shannen Davis, as well as Professor David Birnbaum from the University of Pittsburgh for teaching us the tricks of the trade.

Princeton University "About WordNet." WordNet. Princeton University. 2010. <http://wordnet.princeton.edu>